Inventory of the Peters Z. Olins Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Peters Z. Olins Papers
1927-1962
83010
Olins, Peters Z., d. 1962.
4 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, dispatches, writings, financial records, printed matter, photographs, and memorabilia, relating to Latvian foreign relations and émigré affairs.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1997.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1890 Born, Valmiera, Latvia
1919 Enters Latvian diplomatic service
1927 Awarded Ph.D. in history, American University, Washington, D.C.
1928 Author, The Teutonic Knights in Latvia. Promoted to rank of Minister Plenipotentiary.
1962 Died
1910-1914 Student at the University of St. Petersburg
1935-1962 Latvian minister to Argentina and Brazil
Scope and Content of Collection
Acquired in 1997, the Peters Z. Olins papers in the Hoover Institution Archives comprise materials relating to this Latvian diplomat, who served most of his career in posts in Argentina and Brazil. Of perhaps most historical interest in the collection is the official correspondence exchanged between Olins and other Latvian representatives in London, Washington, and elsewhere, and especially his correspondence with Alfreds Bilmanis, Latvian ambassador to the United States. This series also includes copies of letters sent between the Foreign Ministry of Latvia and various Latvian legations, and covers the period before and during World War II. From this correspondence, it is possible to reconstruct the Latvian state's evaluation of its situation in the years immediately before its loss of independence in 1940. These materials also document the unsuccessful efforts of Latvian diplomats abroad to restore Latvian sovereignty after the end of the war.
Following the annexation of Latvia by the Soviet Union, many Latvian diplomats in the West, including Olins, retained their official status as representatives of Latvia and continued to exercise their duties. In this regard, the collection contains both correspondence as well as a number of reports written by Olins and sent to the Latvian Legation in the United States. There is also an album of photographs in the collection relating to Olins' life and career, including his early years as a student and a soldier in World War I, when Latvia was a province of the Russian empire.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Latvians in foreign countries.; Argentina--Foreign relations--Latvia.; Brazil--Foreign relations--Latvia.; Latvia--Foreign relations--Argentina.; Latvia--Foreign relations--Brazil.
Occupations
Diplomats--Latvia.
Container List
- Correspondence, 1935-1962
  - Bilmanis, Alfreds., 1941-1948
    Includes letters neither addressed to nor written by Peters Z. Olins
    - 1941-1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1945-1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Foreign Ministry of Brazil, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Foreign Ministry of Latvia.
    Includes correspondence between this ministry and Latvian legations in other countries
    - 1935-1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1939 (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
    - 1940 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Latvian Legation (London), 1950-1962
    - 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 1954-1957 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 1958-1962 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Latvian Legation (Washington, D.C.), 1955-1962 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Émigré publications, 1950-1960 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Letters, with some transcripts of interviews and clippings
  - Naturalization requests, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - General, 1933-1961 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Reports, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Inaugural program, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Clippings, 1935-1940 (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
- Photograph, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  One print depicting Vilhelms Munters and others
- Financial records, 1952-1964 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  Receipts and invoices
- Financial records, 1954-1961 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  One account book
- Olins, Peters Z., The Principle of the Equality of Men in the Movement for International Peace, doctoral thesis submitted to the American University, Washington, D.C., 1927 March. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Typescript
- Printed matter, 1936-1938 (Box 4, Folder 3-6)
- Album of photographs depicting Latvian participation in the commemoration of the fourth centenary of São Paulo, Brazil, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Biographical file, circa 1890s-1960
  - Album of photographs documenting the life and career of Peters Z. Olins, circa 1890s-1960 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Includes photographs depicting Karlis Ulmanis and other Latvian officials
  - Testimonials given to Peters Z. Olins from the Latvian émigré community in Brazil, 1955-1959 (Box 5, Folder 2-4)
  - Certificate of consular authority, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, 1933 February 21 (Box 5, Folder 5)